End Story
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
か... 帰ってきた?
Returned?
町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||
この町に?
To this town?
当時[とうじ]:at that time/in those days, 大学生[だいがくせい]:university student/college student, 反魂[はんごん]:reviving the dead/calling back the spirits of the dead, 法[ほう]:law|method|mood|, 百[ひゃく, もも]:100/hundred, 死体[したい]:dead body/corpse/cadaver
当時大学生だった私が反魂法(はんごんほう)を使って
百年使われた人間の死体から
It was only fifteen years ago that I was in college and had this idea
that I could reanimate a corpse alive for a hundred years to create Ononoki Yotsugi,
斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 余接[よせつ]:cotangent, 不死身[ふじみ]:invulnerability/immortality/insensibility to pain, 式神[しきがみ]:form of magic or divination (e.g. animating objects to act as the sorcerer's agent), 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, 思い立つ[おもいたつ]:to set one's mind on doing/to get the idea of doing/to make up one's mind
斧乃木余接という不死身の式神怪異を
作ろうと思い立ったのが
ちょうど:exactly/precisely|as if, ちょうど:supplies/furniture/fixtures
ちょうど十五年前だからね
an immortal familiar.
不死鳥[ふしちょう]:phoenix, 次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 寄生木[やどりぎ]:mistletoe (esp. European mistletoe, Viscum album)|parasitic plant, 止まる[とまる]:to stop (moving)|to stop (doing, working, being supplied)|to alight, 止まる[とどまる]:to remain/to abide|to be limited to, まさしく:surely/no doubt/evidently, 頃[ころ, ごろ]:(approximate) time|suitable time (or condition)|time of year, 頃[けい]:qing (Chinese unit of land area equal to 100 mu)
そして 不死鳥が次の寄生木(やどりぎ)に止まったのも
まさしくその頃だ
The phoenix also found its next host around then.
初代[しょだい]:first generation/founder, 構成[こうせい]:organization/organisation/configuration, 灰[はい]:ash/ashes, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 集合[しゅうごう]:gathering/assembly|set, 頃[ころ, ごろ]:(approximate) time|suitable time (or condition)|time of year, 頃[けい]:qing (Chinese unit of land area equal to 100 mu), 愚考[ぐこう]:foolish idea/one's humble opinion
だから彼が 初代の彼を構成する灰が この町に集合したのは
その頃のことなんじゃないかと おねーさんは愚考するねえ
That's why I'm willing to bet that the ashes of the first oddity slayer gathered here around the same time.
Fifteen Years Earlier
連想[れんそう]:association (of ideas)/being reminded (of something)/suggestion, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
十五年前と言えばもうひとつ
僕には連想できてしまうこともあった
There's something else that happened
around fifteen years ago, on that note.
翼[つばさ, よく]:wing|Chinese "Wings" constellation (one of the 28 mansions)|counter for birds or bird wings, 三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 歳[さい]:-years-old|ability/gift, 歳[とし]:year|age|past one's prime, 頃[ころ, ごろ]:(approximate) time|suitable time (or condition)|time of year, 頃[けい]:qing (Chinese unit of land area equal to 100 mu)
羽川翼が 羽川翼という名前になったのが
あいつが三歳だかの頃
Hanekawa Tsubasa was given her
current name when she was three.
即ち[すなわち]:that is/namely/i.e.
即ち十五年前じゃあなかったっけ?
Therefore, fifteen years ago.
Artifact spirit.
憑喪神
不死鳥[ふしちょう]:phoenix
不死鳥
Phoenix.
猫[ねこ, ネコ]:cat|shamisen|geisha||, 猫[ねこま]:cat
猫
Cat.
焦点を絞る[しょうてんをしぼる]:to narrow the focus/to focus attention (on)/to concentrate (on)
いや それを言い出したら 何も十五年前だけに
焦点を絞ることはないのだ
No. Just because those three events happened fifteen years ago doesn't mean they're all connected.
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., 今まで[いままで]:until now/so far/up to the present, 瞬間[しゅんかん]:moment/second/instant, スパン:span, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
そういう話なのであれば十五年前から今の今まで
瞬間ではなくスパンで考えていい
We should be thinking of it as the start of a
time span rather than a single point in time.
道に迷う[みちにまよう]:to lose one's way/to get lost, 蝸牛[かたつむり, かぎゅう]:snail|cochlea
十一年前から道に迷った 蝸牛
A snail got lost eleven years ago.
七[しち, なな]:seven|hepta-, 七[チー]:seven, 願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, 叶える[かなえる]:to grant (request, wish)/to answer (prayer)|to fulfill (conditions), 猿[さる, サル]:monkey (esp. the Japanese macaque, Macaca fuscata)|sly person|idiot||, 猿[ましら, まし]:monkey (esp. the Japanese macaque, Macaca fuscata)/ape/non-human primate
七年前に願いを叶えた 猿
A monkey made a wish seven years ago.
A crab lost her weight three years ago.
三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 重い[おもい]:heavy|heavy (feeling)|slow||, 奪う[うばう]:to snatch away/to dispossess/to steal, 蟹[かに, カニ]:crab
三年前に重さを奪った 蟹
わずか:only/merely/(a) little, 二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, ヵ月[かげつ]:months (period of), 蛇[へび, じゃ]:snake|serpent/large snake, 範疇[はんちゅう]:category
わずか二ヵ月前の
蛇のことすら範疇(はんちゅう)
The snake two months ago also falls into it.
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 語る[かたる]:to talk about|to recite|to indicate, 数々[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数々[かずかず]:many/numerous/various, 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, 灰[はい]:ash/ashes, 風に乗る[かぜにのる]:to ride upon the winds, 流れる[ながれる]:to stream|to be washed away|to drift||
まさか... この町で語られていた数々の怪異譚が
すべて その灰とやらが風に乗って流れてきたせいだと言うんですか?
Are you saying that all the oddities we've covered
so far were the direct fault of the ashes blown here?
Ash
じゃん:isn't it
そんなわけないじゃん
Of course not.
余弦[よげん]:cosine, 達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, 余接[よせつ]:cotangent, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||
余弦達が余接を作ったのは
この町でのことじゃあないしね
Yozuru and the others didn't make Yotsugi here in this town.
Snake   Ash   Bee   Ash   Monkey   Ash   Cow   Ash   Cat   Ash
遠い[とおい]:far/distant, 困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered
遠困ってだけさ
It's just the connector.
符号[ふごう]:sign/mark|sign (e.g. positive, negative)
思わせぶりな符号とでも言おうかな
Call it a suggestive code if you want.
基本的[きほんてき]:fundamental/standard/basic, 達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, 遭遇[そうぐう]:encounter/being confronted with (e.g. difficulty)/meeting with (e.g. accident), 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost
基本的に きみ達が遭遇した怪異は
きみ達のせいだ
The oddities you've encountered are your own fault.
責任[せきにん]:duty/responsibility (incl. supervision of staff)|liability, 逃れ[のがれ]:escaping/evading, 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
責任逃れは許さない
I won't let you dodge the bullet there.
ただし:but/however/provided that
ただし...
However...
The reason that Kiss-Shot Acerola-Orion Heart-Under-Blade came to this city during spring break
春休み[はるやすみ]:spring break/spring vacation, アセロラオリオン:acerola (Malpighia glabra)/Barbados cherry, アセロラオリオン:Orion, ハート:heart, アンダー:under, ブレード:blade, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 訪れる[おとずれる, おとづれる]:to visit/to call on|to arrive
春休み キスショット・アセロラオリオン・ハートアンダーブレードが
この町を訪れたのは
is for no other purpose than these ashes.
間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman), 灰[はい]:ash/ashes
間違いなく
その灰ありきのことだっただろうがね
End Story
Shinobu Mail Part Four
馬鹿[ばか, バカ]:fool|trivial matter|foolish|
馬鹿なことを言う
Don't be ridiculous.
アロハ:aloha, 小僧[こぞう]:youngster|young Buddhist priest|young shopboy, 妹[いもうと]:younger sister, 妹[いも]:darling (only of a woman)|one's sister|friend
それでもあのアロハ小僧の妹か
Are you really the sister of the Hawaiian shirt man?
She isn't his sister
儂[わし]:I/me (used by elderly males), 国[くに]:country|region|national government||, 訪問[ほうもん]:call/visit, 富士山[ふじさん, ふじやま]:Mount Fuji/Mt. Fuji/Fujiyama
儂があのとき この国を訪問したのは
富士山が見たかったからじゃぞ
The reason I came to this country
was because I wanted to see Mt. Fuji.
富士山[ふじさん, ふじやま]:Mount Fuji/Mt. Fuji/Fujiyama
だけどこの山は富士山じゃあないよ
This hill isn't Mt. Fuji, y'know?
静岡県[しずおかけん]:Shizuoka prefecture (Chuubu area), 山梨県[やまなしけん]:Yamanashi prefecture (Chuubu area)
ここは静岡県でも山梨県でもない
We're not in Shizuoka or Yamanashi prefecture, either.
道に迷う[みちにまよう]:to lose one's way/to get lost, 三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 吸血鬼[きゅうけつき]:vampire/bloodsucker, ハンター:hunter, 追う[おう]:to chase|to follow (a set order, a trend, etc.)|to drive out||
道に迷ったのかい?
三人の吸血鬼ハンターに追われて?
Did you get lost when the three vampire hunters chased you?
You didn't.
違うね
道に迷う[みちにまよう]:to lose one's way/to get lost
きみは道に迷ったのではなく
You didn't get lost.
You were led
導く[みちびく]:to guide/to lead|to derive
導かれたんだよ
to this town.
町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||
この町に
導く[みちびく]:to guide/to lead|to derive
導かれ...
Led...
なんという:how (beautiful, etc.)
なんというか
How can I put this?
振り回す[ふりまわす]:to wield|to display (one's knowledge)|to abuse (one's power)|, 出来事[できごと, できこと]:incident/affair/happening, たった:only/merely/but, 一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 収斂[しゅうれん]:astringency|extraction (of taxes)|convergence, 語り[かたり]:talk|narration|topic
僕がこれまで振り回されてきたすべての出来事がその
たった一人の男に収斂(しゅうれん)していくような臥煙さんの語りが
I felt like, according to Gaen, everything I went through could be traced back to that man.
It creeped me out.
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
気持ち悪い
否[ひ]:no/the noes, 否[いいえ, いいや]:no|well|you're welcome
否
Well, no.
単に[たんに]:simply/merely/only, 不快[ふかい]:displeasure/discomfort|indisposition
単に不快なのか
It was just unpleasant.
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
なのになんだよ この気持ちは
What was it that I felt?
まるで:quite/entirely|as if, 嫉妬[しっと]:jealousy/envy, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
まるでこれじゃあ
嫉妬(しっと)しているみたいじゃないか
This feels almost like jealousy?
りえん:theatrical world, りえん:divorce/dissolution of adoption
ありえん
Impossible.
That isn't possible.
りえん:theatrical world, りえん:divorce/dissolution of adoption
そんなことはありえんのじゃ
あやつ:he/she/that guy
あやつは死んだ
He died.
死んだのじゃ
He's dead.
説得[せっとく]:persuasion, 耳を貸す[みみをかす]:to lend an ear to/to listen to, 自ら[おのずから]:naturally/as a matter of course, 自ら[みずから]:oneself|for one's self/personally, 命[いのち]:life|lifetime|most important thing||, 命[めい]:command|life|destiny, 投げ打つ[なげうつ]:to abandon/to throw away/to fling away, 大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||, 間抜け[まぬけ]:stupidity/idiot/dunce
の説得にも耳を貸さず
自ら命を投げ打った大間抜けじゃ
The fool wouldn't listen to what I had to say.
こじつけ:distortion/stretch/strained interpretation, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
うぬの言っておることは
ただのこじつけに過ぎぬ
All of this is just your wild interpretation.
儂[わし]:I/me (used by elderly males), 方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action), 音痴[おんち]:tone-deafness|tone-deaf|having no sense (of something), 馬鹿[ばか, バカ]:fool|trivial matter|foolish|
儂の方向音痴を馬鹿にするな
And so what if I got lost?
You're getting pretty assertive, Shinobu.
随分[ずいぶん]:very/extremely|contemptible, 主張[しゅちょう]:claim/insistence/assertion
随分と主張が強いじゃないか 忍ちゃん
It almost seems like it would be a problem for you had he survived.
まるで:quite/entirely|as if, 初代[しょだい]:first generation/founder, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
それじゃあまるで
初代の彼に生きてられたら困るみたいだよ?
Shouldn't we be offering you our congratulations
that your beloved slave survived and is regenerating?
愛しい[いとしい]:lovely/dear/beloved, 奴隷[どれい]:slave/servant|slavery, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, たとする:to appreciate/to be thankful, まさに:exactly/surely|right then, 復活[ふっかつ]:revival (e.g. musical)/come-back|restoration, 遂げる[とげる]:to accomplish/to achieve|to arrive at (a certain outcome), むしろ:rather/better/instead, むしろ:woven mat (esp. one made of straw)|seat, 大いに[おおいに]:very/much/greatly, 言祝ぐ[ことほぐ]:to congratulate/to wish (someone) well/to celebrate
きみの愛(いと)しい奴隷が生きていたとするなら
今まさに復活を遂げようとしているなら むしろ大いに言祝(ことほ)ぐべきだろうに
Congratulations
I can check some local bars out if you want to celebrate.
パーティ:party, 手配[てはい]:arrangement/preparations|search (by police), あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
なんなら私がパーティの手配をしてあげてもいいんだよ?
Don't meddle in this, specialist.
あまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 踏み込む[ふみこむ]:to step into (e.g. someone else's territory)/to break into|to come to grips with, 専門家[せんもんか]:specialist/expert/professional
あまり踏み込むなよ 専門家
儂[わし]:I/me (used by elderly males), デリケート:delicate/sensitive/subtle, 部分[ぶぶん]:portion/section/part, 踏み込む[ふみこむ]:to step into (e.g. someone else's territory)/to break into|to come to grips with
儂のデリケートな部分に 踏み込むな
Don't meddle in what causes me grief.
いったい:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")/...in the world (e.g. "why in the world?")|one object, いったい:region/zone/whole place
うぬが四百年前の
いったい何を知っておると言うのじゃ
What do you think you know about
what happened four hundred years ago?
私は何でも知っているよ
I know everything.
私に知らないことはない
There's nothing I don't know.
待ち合わせる[まちあわせる]:to rendezvous/to meet at a prearranged place and time/to arrange to meet, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 公園[こうえん]:(public) park, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 移す[うつす]:to change|to change the object of one's interest or focus|to spend or take time||, ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive
待ち合わせ場所を 公園から神社に移したことにも
ちゃんと理由がある
There's a reason we met here at
the shrine and not in the park, too.
Go to
- >
Shrine of the
Polar Snake
質問[しつもん]:question/inquiry/enquiry, 湖[みずうみ]:lake, 湖[こ]:lake (in place names)
ひとつ質問してもいいかな 伊豆湖さん
Can I ask a question, Izuko?
Of course, Kanbaru Suruga.
いいよ 神原駿河さん
えっと:let me see/well/errr ..., そいつ:he/she|that, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 流れる[ながれる]:to stream|to be washed away|to drift||, 時点[じてん]:point in time/occasion, 灰[はい]:ash/ashes
えっと そいつは十五年前
この町に流れてきた時点でさえほぼ灰だったわけだろう?
He was mostly ash when he arrived here fifteen years ago, right?
So how was that cycle broken?
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||, きっかけ:chance/start/cue, サイクル:cycle, 終わり[おわり]:the end
だったら一体 何をきっかけにそのサイクルは終わり
鎧[よろい]:armor/armour, 武者[むしゃ]:warrior, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 現れる[あらわれる]:to appear/to come in sight|to be expressed (e.g. emotions)
ああして鎧武者として
阿良々木先輩の前に現れたのだ?
How did he come to appear before Araragi as a suit of armor?
どうしてだと思うかな? 神原駿河さんは
What do you think, Kanbaru Suruga?
見当[けんとう]:estimate|direction|registration mark (printing)|
見当はつかないが...
I don't really have a clue,
理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive, 待ち合わせる[まちあわせる]:to rendezvous/to meet at a prearranged place and time/to arrange to meet, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 変える[かえる]:to change/to alter|to reform, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
その理由が 待ち合わせ場所を変えたことと
何か関係があるということだろうか?
but I assume it's related to why you changed the place we met.
鋭い[するどい]:sharp (blade)|sharp (pain)|perceptive|
鋭いねえ
You're clever.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 放っておく[ほうっておく, ほっておく]:to leave alone/to leave as is/to ignore, 惜しい[おしい]:regrettable|precious|too good for|, 才能[さいのう]:talent/ability
本当 野(や)に放っておくには惜しい才能だ
Your intellect is being wasted.
私自身[わたしじしん, わたくしじしん]:myself, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||, 身分[みぶん]:social position/social status, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
私自身 先輩と呼ばれることの多い身分だから
そう思うのかもしれないけれど
I might be saying this because I'm often looked up to as well,
願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself, こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 支える[ささえる]:to support/to prop|to hold at bay, 支える[つかえる, つっかえる]:to stick|to be unavailable|to be piled up (e.g. of work)||, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair), 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
願わくは神原駿河さん きみには
こちらの先輩を支えてあげて欲しいものだよ
but do please support him however you can, Kanbaru Suruga.
Timeline
初代[しょだい]:first generation/founder, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
十五年前 初代の彼はこの町に帰ってきた
Fifteen years ago he returned to this town.
漂泊[ひょうはく]:roaming/drifting about/wandering, 終える[おえる]:to finish|to graduate, 故郷[ふるさと, こきょう]:home town/birthplace|ruins, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 流れ着く[ながれつく]:to drift to/to be washed ashore
漂泊(ひょうはく)を終え
故郷となるこの町に流れ着いた
He ended his years adrift to wash up in his hometown.
永劫[えいごう]:eternity/perpetuity, 思える[おもえる]:to seem/to appear likely, 地獄[じごく]:hell, 巡り[めぐり]:circumference|tour|circulation (e.g. of blood), ゴール:goal/basket (basketball)/finishing line, 迎える[むかえる]:to go out to meet|to receive|to accept (e.g. as a member of a group or family)||
永劫(えいごう)とも思えた地獄巡りは
ゴールを迎えた
His seemingly endless purgatory came to an end.
Hometown?
故郷[ふるさと, こきょう]:home town/birthplace|ruins
故郷?
流れ着く[ながれつく]:to drift to/to be washed ashore, 灰[はい]:ash/ashes, 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 粒[つぶ, つび]:grain/bead|counter for small round objects including grains, seeds, pills, drops, 集まる[あつまる]:to gather/to collect/to assemble, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 地点[ちてん]:site/point on a map/spot
そして流れ着いた灰の一粒一粒が集まったのが
町のエアスポットとなる地点
And all those little specks of ash and dust
began to assemble at the town's air pocket—
北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine
ここ 北白蛇神社なのだよ
this shrine, the Shrine of the Polar Snake.
Five
Four
Three
Two
One
ご覧[ごらん]:(please) try to|(please) look|seeing, 通り[とおり]:avenue|coming and going|flow (of water, air, etc.)||, 通り[どおり]:in accordance with|roughly|Street, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 荒れ果てる[あれはてる]:to fall into ruin/to be desolated
ご覧の通り この神社は荒れ果てている
As you can see, this shrine is a mere ruin.
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 昔[むかし]:olden days/former
だがもちろん
ずっと昔からこうだったわけではない
Of course, it wasn't always like this.
時点[じてん]:point in time/occasion, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, きちんと:properly/accurately|neatly, 整備[せいび]:maintenance/servicing|putting in place
十五年前の時点では
この神社はまだきちんと整備されていた
Fifteen years ago, this was a fine and orderly shrine.
小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny, まとまる:to be collected/to be settled/to be in order, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine
小さくまとまったいい神社だったそうだよ
Small and compact.
場合[ばあい]:case/situation, 小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny, まとまる:to be collected/to be settled/to be in order, 悪口[あっこう, わるくち]:abuse/insult/slander, 褒め言葉[ほめことば]:words of praise/eulogy/compliment
この場合 "小さくまとまった"というのは
悪口ではなく 褒め言葉だ
I don't mean that in a belittling way, but purely in praise.
小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny, まとめる:to collect/to put (it all) together|to summarize
小さくまとめなければならないんだ
It has to be small and compact,
なぜならここは エアスポットだからね
because this is an air pocket.
怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost
怪異のエアスポット
An air pocket for oddities.
Easy for them to appear; easy for them to gather.
やすい:cheap/inexpensive|calm, やすい:easy|likely to .../have a tendency to ..., 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 集まる[あつまる]:to gather/to collect/to assemble
出やすい場所 集まりやすい場所
怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, 以前[いぜん]:ago/since/before, 集結[しゅうけつ]:massing (of troops)/gathering, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
怪異以前の"よくないもの"が集結する場所
Evil things even older than oddities gather here.
And this is also where oddities end.
怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, 終結[しゅうけつ]:end/close, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
そして怪異が 終結する場所
Controlling these locations allows you to prevent undesired developments.
ポイント:point, 要所[ようしょ]:important point/important position, 押さえる[おさえる]:to pin something down|to seize|to gain control of something|, アクシデント:accident, 事前[じぜん]:prior/beforehand/in advance, 回避[かいひ]:evasion/avoidance
そういうポイントポイント 要所要所を押さえれば
アクシデントを事前に防げる 回避できる
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen, 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, 蒐集[しゅうしゅう]:gathering up/collection/accumulation
メメお兄ちゃんの仕事は起こった怪異譚の
蒐集(しゅうしゅう)だけれど
Meme's job is collecting stories of oddities,
なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 本来[ほんらい]:originally|essentially|proper
私なんかの仕事は 本来 こっちだね
but mine is different.
起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen, 片付ける[かたづける]:to tidy up|to settle (problem)|to finish||, 予防[よぼう]:prevention/precaution/protection against
つまりことが起こる前に片付けるという予防
I prevent oddities from appearing in the first place.
逆[ぎゃく]:reverse|converse (of a hypothesis, etc.)|inverse (function), 逆[さか]:inverse/reverse, 各地[かくち]:every place/various places, 点在[てんざい]:being dotted with/being scattered, スポット:spot, 要所[ようしょ]:important point/important position, 抑え込む[おさえこむ]:to shut out one's opponents/to stop the other side from scoring, アクシデント:accident
逆に 各地に点在するそれらのスポット
要所要所を抑え込めなければ アクシデントは防げない
Therefore, I have to control these locations or I can have no impact.
It is because of this
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
ここはそういう場所だったからこそ
"Air pocket for oddities"
that an incomparably more famous exorcist than me
built this shrine and enshrined a spirit to control the area.
かつて:once/before|never yet, なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something, 比べ物[くらべもの]:something worthy of comparison/something being compared, 陰陽[いんよう, おんみょう]:cosmic dual forces/yin and yang/sun and moon, etc., 師[し]:teacher|religious leader|specialist|, 社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc., 建てる[たてる]:to build/to construct, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 祀る[まつる]:to deify/to enshrine|to pray, 抑え込む[おさえこむ]:to shut out one's opponents/to stop the other side from scoring, かかる:to span/to bridge/to cross, かかる:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang
かつて 私なんかとは比べ物にならないほどに名のある陰陽師が
社を建てて神様を祀(まつ)って 抑え込みにかかったというわけだ
概ね[おおむね]:in general/generally|gist, うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious
それは概ねうまく行っていた
It largely succeeded.
きちんと:properly/accurately|neatly, 防犯[ぼうはん]:prevention of crime, 機能[きのう]:function/facility/faculty, 働く[はたらく]:to work|to function|to commit (e.g. a crime)|
きちんと防犯機能は働いていた
The security system was working.
寄る[よる]:to approach|to gather (in one place)|to stop by (while on one's way to another place)||, 集める[あつめる]:to collect/to assemble/to gather, 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, 材料[ざいりょう]:ingredients|material (for a novel, experiment, etc.)|basis (for a decision)|, 適度[てきど]:moderate, 散らす[ちらす]:to scatter|to disperse|to resolve (a symptom, condition, etc.)||
ここに寄り集められる 怪異の材料となるような"よくないもの"は
適度に散らされていた
Some of the dark things that form the essence of oddities were dispersed by it.
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
いい神様がいたんだね
We had a good spirit here.
何事[なにごと]:what|nothing (with neg. verb)|something or other, 限度[げんど]:limit/bounds
だけど何事にも限度がある
But all things come to an end.
えーっと:let me see/well/errr ..., こよみ:calendar/almanac, 受験生[じゅけんせい]:student preparing for or taking examinations (usu. entrance exams)/test-taker
えーっと こよみん
きみは今受験生だそうだけれど
Koyomin, you're studying for exams, right?
お守り[おまもり]:charm/amulet, お守り[おもり]:babysitting/babysitter|taking care of, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
じゃあお守りとか持っているかな?
Are you carrying a good luck charm?
お守り[おまもり]:charm/amulet, お守り[おもり]:babysitting/babysitter|taking care of
お守り
Charms...
消費期限[しょうひきげん]:"use by" date (food)/expiry date
あれって消費期限があるの 知っているかな?
Did you know charms have an expiration date?
袋[ふくろ]:bag|skin of an orange (and other like fruits)|dead end|, 袋[たい]:counter for things inside a bag, 守り札[まもりふだ]:paper charm/talisman, 破れる[われる]:to break|to split|to be divided|, 破れる[やぶれる]:to get torn/to tear|to be broken off (of negotiations, etc.), 期限切れ[きげんぎれ]:expiration of a term/becoming overdue
袋の中に入っている守り札が破れたときが期限切れ
They expire when they break.
霊験[れいげん, れいけん]:miraculous efficacy/miracle/miraculous virtue, あらたか:clearly miraculous/remarkably miraculous/striking, アイテム:item, 無限[むげん]:infinity/infinitude|infinite, 効能[こうのう, くのう]:effect/efficacy/virtue, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
霊験(れいげん)あらたかなアイテムも
無限の効能を持つわけではないという話で
Even items of august power can be limited by time,
and this shrine, together with its spirit, reached its limit fifteen years ago.
神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 祀る[まつる]:to deify/to enshrine|to pray, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, リミット:limit, 迎える[むかえる]:to go out to meet|to receive|to accept (e.g. as a member of a group or family)||
この神社も 祀られていた神様も
十五年前 リミットを迎えた
件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 管理者[かんりしゃ]:manager/landlord|root (user), まして:still more/to say nothing of|still less, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 責める[せめる]:to condemn|to urge|to torture|, 酷[こく]:severe/harsh/stringent
いやでも その件で 神社の管理者や
ましてや神様を責めるのは酷と言うものだ
You can't blame the priests—let alone the spirit—for this.
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 想定外[そうていがい]:beyond expectations/beyond what one expected/not foreseen
さすがに想定外だよ
These are just unforeseen developments.
That the first kin of the legendary vampire—
伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore, 吸血鬼[きゅうけつき]:vampire/bloodsucker, 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 眷属[けんぞく]:(one's) family/dependents|follower
伝説の吸血鬼の第一眷属が
灰[はい]:ash/ashes, 四方[しほう, よも]:the four cardinal directions|surroundings|many countries||, 八方[はっぽう]:all sides/the four cardinal directions and the four ordinal directions|large hanging lantern, 集まる[あつまる]:to gather/to collect/to assemble, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 限度を超える[げんどをこえる]:to go beyond the limit/to pass the limit
その灰が 四方八方から集まってくるだなんて
ものの限度を超えている
rather, his ash, scattered across the seven seas,
would assemble here, was beyond anyone's foresight.
限界[げんかい]:limit/bound
限界だ
Beyond their limits.
結果[けっか]:result/consequence|coming to fruition, 一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, 北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 崩壊[ほうかい]:collapse/crumbling|decay
結果 十五年前 一度
この北白蛇神社は崩壊した
As a result, the Shrine of the Polar Snake fell into disrepair fifteen years ago.
オカルト:occult, 的[てき]:-like/typical, 的[まと]:mark/target, 物理的[ぶつりてき]:physical
オカルト的にも 物理的にもね
Both spiritually and physically.
灰[はい]:ash/ashes, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 潰す[つぶす]:to smash|to shut down|to thwart||
灰の状態で神社をひとつ潰すとは
Your kind ravaged this shrine with naught but his ash.
眷属[けんぞく]:(one's) family/dependents|follower, 大した[たいした]:considerable/great/important
忍ちゃん きみの眷属は本当
大したものだ
Very impressive, Shinobu!
元[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 元[げん]:unknown (e.g. in an equation)|element (of a set)|yuan (monetary unit of China)|, 専門家[せんもんか]:specialist/expert/professional
元が専門家だからというのもあるんだろうけどね
He was a specialist once, after all.
こよみ:calendar/almanac
どうしたかな こよみん
What is it, Koyomin?
納得[なっとく]:consent/assent|understanding, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face
何かに納得したみたいな顔をして
You look like you just agreed with something.
先日[せんじつ]:the other day/a few days ago, タイム:time, スリップ:slip (i.e. slide), 過去[かこ]:the past|a past (i.e. a personal history one would prefer remained secret)|past (tense)|, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 荒れ果てる[あれはてる]:to fall into ruin/to be desolated, うっかり:carelessly/thoughtlessly/inadvertently, 説明がつく[せつめいがつく]:to explain adequately/to be accountable, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.), たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however, 感じ[かんじ]:feeling/sense/impression
ああ つい先日タイムスリップした過去の世界で 十一年前の北白蛇神社が
今以上に荒れ果てていたことに うっかり説明がついてしまったって感じかな?
Oh, did you recall the even more dilapidated state this shrine was in when you time-traveled to eleven years ago?
Yes.
そうだよ
初代[しょだい]:first generation/founder, 仕業[しわざ]:deed (esp. negative)/act/action
それは 初代の彼の仕業だ
That was his doing.
要所[ようしょ]:important point/important position, 抑える[おさえる]:to pin something down|to seize|to gain control of something|, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 吸血鬼[きゅうけつき]:vampire/bloodsucker, 眷属[けんぞく]:(one's) family/dependents|follower, 抑え込む[おさえこむ]:to shut out one's opponents/to stop the other side from scoring
要所を抑えたはずの神社は
吸血鬼の眷属を抑え込めなかった
This shrine was meant to control the location, but it couldn't control the vampire kin.
参考[さんこう]:reference/consultation, 後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|, 一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, 二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol), 三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 亘る[わたる]:to cross over/to go across|to extend, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, リニューアル:renovation/overhaul/update
参考までに言っておくと その後一度ならず二度三度に亘り
この神社はリニューアルされようとしたそうなんだけれどね
Now, there were attempts to renovate the shrine several times,
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 空っぽ[からっぽ]:empty/vacant/hollow, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 補修[ほしゅう]:repair/mending, 建設的[けんせつてき]:constructive, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
神様がいない空っぽの神社なんて
補修したところで建設的な意味がない
but that's meaningless without a spirit enshrined here.
Purity in Spirit
Every time it was renovated,
it broke down; was ravaged again.
リニューアル:renovation/overhaul/update, しようとする:to try and do something/to attempt to do something, 崩れる[くずれる]:to collapse|to get out of shape|to break down||, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through, 荒れ果てる[あれはてる]:to fall into ruin/to be desolated
リニューアルしようとするたびに崩れて
壊れて 荒れ果てた
The real problem is that Shinobu—
厄介[やっかい]:trouble/burden|care
厄介なのは 忍ちゃん
アセロラオリオン:acerola (Malpighia glabra)/Barbados cherry, アセロラオリオン:Orion, ハート:heart, アンダー:under, ブレード:blade, 眷属[けんぞく]:(one's) family/dependents|follower, 初代[しょだい]:first generation/founder
と言うか キスショット・アセロラオリオン・ハートアンダーブレードや
その眷属となる初代の彼には
well, Kiss-Shot Acerola-Orion Heart-Under-Blade and her kin attract oddities with their mere existence.
存在[そんざい]:existence/being, 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, 呼び込む[よびこむ]:to call in/to invite/to bring in, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.), 的[てき]:-like/typical, 的[まと]:mark/target, 強力[きょうりょく]:powerful/strong, 強力[ごうりき]:herculean strength/mountain carrier-guide
存在するだけで怪異を呼び込んでしまう
誘蛾的な強力さがあるということだ
達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 訪れる[おとずれる, おとづれる]:to visit/to call on|to arrive, 際[きわ, ぎわ]:edge/brink|time, 際[さい]:on the occasion of/circumstances/juncture, 荒れ果てる[あれはてる]:to fall into ruin/to be desolated, 境内[けいだい]:grounds (esp. of shrines and temples)/compound/churchyard, 満ち満ちる[みちみちる]:to be full to the brim
それこそ十一年前 きみ達がこの神社を訪れた際には
荒れ果てたこの境内には"よくないもの"が満ち満ちていたのだろう?
And eleven years ago, when you visited this shrine,
this shrine was full of such things, right?
濃度[のうど]:concentration/thickness|cardinality, 集まる[あつまる]:to gather/to collect/to assemble, 不思議[ふしぎ]:wonder/miracle/strange
どうしてそこまでの濃度で集まっていたのか
不思議だったと思うけれど
You must have wondered why so many of them had gathered here.
初代[しょだい]:first generation/founder, 灰[はい]:ash/ashes, 寄せ集める[よせあつめる]:to put together/to gather/to collect, 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, 材料[ざいりょう]:ingredients|material (for a novel, experiment, etc.)|basis (for a decision)|
なんのことはない それは初代の彼が
彼の灰が寄せ集めた怪異の材料だったんだよ
They were the components of the oddities that he,
the first kin, his ashes, had attracted.
材料[ざいりょう]:ingredients|material (for a novel, experiment, etc.)|basis (for a decision)|
材料であり
Components—
食料[しょくりょう]:food
食料
food.
説明[せつめい]:explanation/exposition, 専門知識[せんもんちしき]:expertise/special knowledge/technical knowledge, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, こよみ:calendar/almanac, だいぶん:considerably/greatly/a lot, 予想[よそう]:expectation/anticipation/prediction
ここまで説明すれば 専門知識を持たないこよみんにも
だいぶん予想はついてきたんじゃないのかな
You should have some idea what happened now, even if you aren't a specialist, Koyomin.
集まる[あつまる]:to gather/to collect/to assemble, 初代[しょだい]:first generation/founder, 灰[はい]:ash/ashes, 輪廻[りんね]:samsara/endless cycle of death and rebirth, サイクル:cycle, 脱する[だっする]:to escape from/to get out
どうしてここに集まった初代の彼の灰が
輪廻のサイクルから脱したのか
You should know why his ashes were able to break out of the endless cycle of death and rebirth.
そうだよ
Yes.
神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 集まる[あつまる]:to gather/to collect/to assemble, やすい:cheap/inexpensive|calm, やすい:easy|likely to .../have a tendency to ..., 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 初代[しょだい]:first generation/founder, 集める[あつめる]:to collect/to assemble/to gather, 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, たとする:to appreciate/to be thankful
この神社が"集まりやすい場所"で
初代の彼が"集めやすい怪異"だったとするなら
Oddities easily appear at this shrine, and he attracted them,
即ち[すなわち]:that is/namely/i.e., アクシデント:accident, 起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen, 条件[じょうけん]:condition/conditions/term, 揃う[そろう]:to become complete|to be equal|to gather, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
即ち アクシデントが起こる条件が
揃ってしまったということだ
so it synergized.
アクシデント:accident, 重なる[かさなる]:to be piled up|to come one after another|to overlap (each other), 重なる[おもなる]:main/principal/important
アクシデントが 重なった
So it was a perfect storm.
初代[しょだい]:first generation/founder, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 境内[けいだい]:grounds (esp. of shrines and temples)/compound/churchyard, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 体力[たいりょく]:stamina/endurance|strength of an organization (e.g. profitability, productivity, economic clout, stability, growth potential), 回復[かいふく]:restoration/rehabilitation|recovery (from an illness), 食事[しょくじ]:meal|to eat, 続ける[つづける]:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
初代の彼は この神社の境内で 神様のいない神社の境内で
ずっとずっと 体力を回復させるための食事を続けていた
He kept eating to recover his strength on
these shrine grounds where no spirit dwells.
灰[はい]:ash/ashes, 無[む]:nothing/naught|un-, 無[ぶ]:un-/non-|bad ..., 繰り返す[くりかえす]:to repeat/to do something over again, 生活[せいかつ]:living/life (one's daily existence)/livelihood, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
灰と無を繰り返す生活は これで終わった
This was the end of the ash and the void.
始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from), 亘る[わたる]:to cross over/to go across|to extend, 悲劇的[ひげきてき]:tragic, 復活[ふっかつ]:revival (e.g. musical)/come-back|restoration, 劇[げき]:drama/play|powerful drug
始まったのは そこから十五年に亘る
悲劇的な彼の 復活劇だった
This began a fifteen-year story of his sad revival.
復活[ふっかつ]:revival (e.g. musical)/come-back|restoration, 劇[げき]:drama/play|powerful drug
復活劇
A revival play.
ひょっと:possibly/perhaps|unintentionally, 復讐[ふくしゅう]:revenge, 劇[げき]:drama/play|powerful drug, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
ひょっとするとそれは
復讐(ふくしゅう)劇だったかもしれないけれども
Or, perhaps, a revenge play.
頃合い[ころあい]:suitable time/good time|propriety
いい頃合いだなあ
Good time.
概ね[おおむね]:in general/generally|gist, 説明[せつめい]:explanation/exposition, 終える[おえる]:to finish|to graduate
概ね説明は終えたつもりだけれど
I'm more or less done with my explanation.
こよみ:calendar/almanac, 他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters)
こよみん 忍ちゃん 神原駿河さん
他に何かわからないことはあるかい?
Any questions? Koyomin? Shinobu? Kanbaru Suruga?
I still have a ton of questions.
まだまだ:still some way to go before the goal/still more to come/much more, 全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely, だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood)
い いや まだまだ全然わからないことだらけですけど
そもそも:in the first place/to begin with|... the heck (e.g. "what the heck?"), 達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend
そ そもそも 僕達はこのあとどうすればいいんですか?
I mean, what are we even supposed to do now?
達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
何をさせたくて
あなたは僕達に仕事を手伝わそうと
What do you want us to do? What was the point of this?
You need to take responsibility.
責任を取る[せきにんをとる]:to take responsibility, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
責任を取ってもらうのさ
Therefore...
だから
取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
取らせてあげるのさ
I will allow you to.
責任[せきにん]:duty/responsibility (incl. supervision of staff)|liability, 引き取る[ひきとる]:to take over|to take charge of|to retire to a private place, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
責任を 引き取らせてあげるのさ
I'm giving you a chance to take responsibility.
こよみ:calendar/almanac
こよみんと それに 忍ちゃんには
You and Shinobu.
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, 斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 乃[の]:possessive particle, 木[き]:tree/shrub|wood, 木[もく]:Thursday|wood (first of the five elements), 一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 片付ける[かたづける]:to tidy up|to settle (problem)|to finish||, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule
最初は 斧乃木ちゃん一人で
片付ける仕事の予定だったって言ってましたよね
You said that you originally wanted to have Ononoki take care of it alone.
計算[けいさん]:calculation/reckoning|forecast, 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 状況[じょうきょう]:state of affairs (around you)/situation/circumstances
今は計算外の状況だって
You said this was all unforeseen.
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 計画[けいかく]:plan/project/schedule, 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
じゃあ 最初はどういう計画だったのか
教えてもらってもいいですか?
Could you tell me what you originally had in mind?
Sure, but there's no way to make it work by now.
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, 実行[じっこう]:practice/practising/performance, 不可能[ふかのう]:impossible, 計画[けいかく]:plan/project/schedule, 仕方ない[しかたない]:it can't be helped/it's inevitable/it's no use
いいけど でも もうどう考えても実行不可能な計画だから
言っても仕方ないよ
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 憶える[おぼえる]:to memorize|to learn|to feel|
メメお兄ちゃんが
どうしてこの町に来たか 憶えてる?
Do you remember why Meme came to this town?
忍が来たから ですよね?
Because Shinobu came here, right?
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive
貝木も確か 同じ理由でした
I believe the same is true of Kaiki.
影[かげ]:shadow|reflection|ominous sign||, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
そして影縫さんは...
貝木から話を聞いてだったような
And Kagenui heard about it from Kaiki.
Yes.
そう
癖[くせ, へき]:habit (often a bad habit, i.e. vice)|peculiarity|crease, 専門家[せんもんか]:specialist/expert/professional, 達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, それぞれ:each/respectively, 似る[にる]:to resemble/to look like|to be similar (in status, condition, etc.), 寄る[よる]:to approach|to gather (in one place)|to stop by (while on one's way to another place)||, 理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 訪れる[おとずれる, おとづれる]:to visit/to call on|to arrive
ひと癖もふた癖もある専門家達が それぞれ
似たり寄ったりの理由でこの町を訪れたわけだが
All those eccentric specialists came here for similar reasons.
調査[ちょうさ]:investigation/examination/inquiry, 結果[けっか]:result/consequence|coming to fruition, 報告[ほうこく]:report/information, 元[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 元[げん]:unknown (e.g. in an equation)|element (of a set)|yuan (monetary unit of China)|, 届く[とどく]:to reach|to be attentive|to be delivered
その調査結果の報告が
私の元に届いた
The results of their investigation were relayed to me.
I'm just that amazing.
And I, collating their reports, was able to find
strange links and tendencies spanning fifteen years.
結果[けっか]:result/consequence|coming to fruition, それぞれ:each/respectively, 上がる[あがる]:to rise|to enter (esp. from outdoors)|to enter (a school)||, 情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, 精査[せいさ]:close investigation/careful examination/scrutiny, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen, 奇妙[きみょう]:strange/queer/curious, 連鎖[れんさ]:chain/chaining|(genetic) linkage, 風向き[かざむき, かぜむき]:wind's direction, こととなる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that
その結果 それぞれから上がってきた情報を精査した結果
この町で十五年前から起こっている奇妙な連鎖を 風向きを 私は知ることとなった
余接[よせつ]:cotangent, 再度[さいど]:twice/again/second time, 町[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 送り込む[おくりこむ]:to send in
というわけで 私は余接を 再度この町に送り込んだ
And so I sent Yotsugi to this town again.
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 内容[ないよう]:subject/contents/matter, 灰[はい]:ash/ashes, 掃除[そうじ]:cleaning/sweeping/dusting
仕事内容は灰掃除
Her job was dusting off this shrine.
簡単[かんたん]:simple/easy|brief, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 清掃[せいそう]:cleaning/clean-up/garbage collection
簡単に言えば 神社の清掃かな
Cleaning it up.
夏休み[なつやすみ]:summer vacation/summer holiday, 最終日[さいしゅうび]:last day/final day, 街中[まちなか]:downtown, 街中[まちじゅう]:the whole town/all over the town/throughout the town, 遭遇[そうぐう]:encounter/being confronted with (e.g. difficulty)/meeting with (e.g. accident), 任務[にんむ]:duty/function/office, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
夏休みの最終日 街中で僕と遭遇したときの彼女は
まだ自分の任務を知らなかったみたいだが
When I met her in town on the last day of summer vacation, she didn't seem like she was on her mission yet.
Ice
Bubblegum
Ice Cream
Sweets for a Penny
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 任務[にんむ]:duty/function/office, 与える[あたえる]:to give (esp. to someone of lower status)|to provide|to assign||
あのあと そんなシンデレラみたいな任務を
与えられていたのか
Was she given this Cinderella task afterwards?
Did she fail, then?
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 失敗[しっぱい]:failure/mistake/blunder
が しかし結局
それは失敗したということだよな?
斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 乃[の]:possessive particle, 木[き]:tree/shrub|wood, 木[もく]:Thursday|wood (first of the five elements), 任務[にんむ]:duty/function/office, 失敗[しっぱい]:failure/mistake/blunder
あの斧乃木ちゃんが任務に失敗するか?
Why would she fail?
She's dutiful enough to save both me and Shinobu in one night.
たった:only/merely/but, 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 晩[ばん]:evening|counter for nights, 両方[りょうほう]:both/both sides/both parties, 命[いのち]:life|lifetime|most important thing||, 命[めい]:command|life|destiny, 救う[すくう]:to rescue from/to help out of/to save, 働き者[はたらきもの]:hard worker/hardworking person
たった一晩のうちに 僕と忍 その両方の命を救ってくれた
働き者の彼女が だぞ?
斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 乃[の]:possessive particle, 木[き]:tree/shrub|wood, 木[もく]:Thursday|wood (first of the five elements), 天然[てんねん]:nature/spontaneity|natural airhead, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
まあでも 斧乃木ちゃん
あれでド天然みたいなところもあるからな
I guess she can be really spontaneous.
Perhaps even she can fail every now and then.
失敗[しっぱい]:failure/mistake/blunder
失敗することもあるのか
他人事[ひとごと, たにんごと]:other people's affairs/somebody else's problem, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, こよみ:calendar/almanac
他人事(ひとごと)みたいに言ってやるなよ こよみん
Don't act like it isn't your fault, Koyomin.
余接[よせつ]:cotangent, 失敗[しっぱい]:failure/mistake/blunder, 達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, 所為[しょい]:act/deed/one's doing, 所為[せい, せえ]:consequence/outcome/result
余接の失敗はきみ達の所為(せい)なんだから
It is, y'know?
達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, 所為[しょい]:act/deed/one's doing, 所為[せい, せえ]:consequence/outcome/result
ぼ 僕達の所為?
Our fault?
ひょっと:possibly/perhaps|unintentionally, 溜まる[たまる]:to collect/to gather/to save, 野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, お札[おさつ]:bill/note (currency), お札[おふだ]:type of household amulet or talisman, issued by a Shinto shrine, hung in the house for protection, 封ずる[ふうずる]:to seal (letter)|to prevent/to forbid, 封ずる[ほうずる]:to enfeoff, 散る[ちる]:to fall (e.g. blossoms, leaves)|to scatter|to disappear||
ひょっとしてですけれど このエアスポットに溜まっていた 忍野のお札(ふだ)で封じて
あとは散るのを待つだけだった"よくないもの"を
You mean because Shinobu and I used up all the evil things that were imprisoned here by Oshino's seals?
エネルギー:energy, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.), 関わり[かかわり]:relation/connection
エネルギーとして 僕と忍が使ってしまったことと
何か関わりがありますか?
Did something come to mind?
してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
忍ちゃんは何もしていないよ
Shinobu didn't do anything.
She didn't have to do anything.
してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
何もしていない 何をするまでもなかったんだ
Coming to this shrine was enough.
神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 十分[じっぷん, じゅっぷん]:10 minutes, 十分[じゅうぶん]:plenty|division into ten|perfectly
この神社に来たというそれだけで 十分だった
正直[しょうじき]:honesty/integrity|honestly, お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 事情[じじょう]:circumstances/consideration/conditions, 察する[さっする]:to guess/to sense|to sympathize with, 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance
正直 メメお兄ちゃんが
どこまで事情を察していたのかは不明だ
To be honest, I don't know how well Meme understood the situation.
多く[おおく]:many/much/largely, 語る[かたる]:to talk about|to recite|to indicate, 報告[ほうこく]:report/information, 最小限[さいしょうげん]:minimum/lowest, 上げる[あげる]:to raise|to do up (one's hair)|to fly (a kite, etc.)||
あいつは多くを語らない男で
報告も最小限しか上げてこないしね
He isn't a man of many words and only told me the bare minimum.
2000 Liter Fire-Fighting Foam Tank
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 手持ち[てもち]:in hand/on hand|handheld, 札[さつ]:note/paper money, 札[ふだ, ふみた]:ticket|label|sign||, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 応急[おうきゅう]:emergency/first-aid, 処置[しょち]:measure/step|medical treatment, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
確かなことはあいつが手持ちの札で
この神社に応急処置をしたというくらいだ
All I know is that he had some stop-gap measures in place with the seals he had available.
応急[おうきゅう]:emergency/first-aid, 処置[しょち]:measure/step|medical treatment, お蔭[おかげ]:grace (of God)|assistance|effects, 初代[しょだい]:first generation/founder, 兵糧[ひょうろう]:(army) provisions/food, 攻め[せめ]:attack|dominant partner of a homosexual relationship|a barrage of, 仕掛ける[しかける]:to start|to challenge|to set (traps), 結果[けっか]:result/consequence|coming to fruition
その応急処置のお蔭で 言うなら初代の彼に兵糧攻(ひょうろうぜ)めを
仕掛けた結果になったわけだが
As a result of his actions, the first kin began to starve,
飢える[うえる, かつえる]:to starve/to thirst/to be hungry, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation, 再び[ふたたび]:again/once more/a second time, 極限[きょくげん]:utmost limits/extremity|limit, 追い込む[おいこむ]:to herd/to corner/to drive
そんな飢えた状態で 彼は
再び極限に追い込まれた状態で
and his progress was undone.
精神[せいしん]:mind/soul/heart, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation
そんな精神状態で 彼は
知った
Back to a minimum of self-awareness, he then saw
アセロラオリオン:acerola (Malpighia glabra)/Barbados cherry, アセロラオリオン:Orion, ハート:heart, アンダー:under, ブレード:blade
キスショット・アセロラオリオン・ハートアンダーブレードを
見た
Kiss-Shot Acerola-Orion Heart-Under-Blade
目撃[もくげき]:witnessing/observing/sighting
四百年ぶりに
目撃した
after four hundred years.
一方的[いっぽうてき]:one-sided/unilateral/arbitrary, 目撃[もくげき]:witnessing/observing/sighting
一方的な目撃だがね
You didn't know he was here.
北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ...
忍ちゃんがここ 北白蛇神社にやって来たのは
そのときが初めてだったんだろう?
That was the first time you went to
the Shrine of the Polar Snake, right?
振り[ふり]:swing|appearance|pretence (pretense)||, 振り[ぶり]:style/manner|after (period of time) again (e.g. meeting again after a year), 目視[もくし]:eyesight/seeing, 力づける[ちからづける]:to encourage (someone)/to cheer (someone) up/to give someone a charge
つまり 忍ちゃんを四百年振りに
目視したことで力づけられ
So, seeing her after four hundred years invigorated his spirit,
鼓舞[こぶ]:inspiration/encouragement, 初代[しょだい]:first generation/founder, 灰[はい]:ash/ashes, 身[み]:body|oneself|one's place|, 身[むくろ]:(dead) body/corpse, ながら:while/during|while, 奮起[ふんき]:stirring/rousing oneself, 飢餓[きが]:starvation/famine/hunger, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation, かかわる:to be affected/to be influenced|to be concerned with, 甦る[よみがえる]:to be resurrected/to be resuscitated|to be recalled (e.g. memories)
鼓舞(こぶ)された初代が 灰の身でありながらも奮起して
飢餓状態にあったにもかかわらず甦った ということなのか?
and encouraged him to rouse his ashes and revive, overcoming his starvation?
ロマンチック:romantic
そんなロマンチックなこと 誰が言った?
It isn't nearly that romantic.
Having someone closely related physically close by
単に[たんに]:simply/merely/only, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being, 近しい[ちかしい]:intimate/close
単に 存在の近しい存在が
Like it's some teen romantic comedy
just gave a strong buff to his status as an oddity.
物理的[ぶつりてき]:physical, 近い[ちかい]:near|close (in time)|close (relationship)||, 距離[きょり]:distance/range, 現れる[あらわれる]:to appear/to come in sight|to be expressed (e.g. emotions), 影響[えいきょう]:influence/effect|to influence, 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||, 初代[しょだい]:first generation/founder, 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, 性[さが, なりくせ]:one's nature/one's destiny|custom, 性[せい]:nature (of a person)|sex|gender|, 急速[きゅうそく]:rapid (e.g. progress), 励起[れいき]:(electrical) excitation
物理的に近い距離に現れたから
その影響を受けて初代の彼の怪異性が急速に励起(れいき)したというだけだよ
余接[よせつ]:cotangent, 任務[にんむ]:duty/function/office, 帯びる[おびる]:to wear (sword, decoration, etc.)|to be entrusted (e.g. with a mission)|to have a trace of
だから余接が任務を帯びてここに来たときには
When Yotsugi attempted to fulfill her mission,
北[きた]:north|the North|North Korea|, 北[ペー]:north wind tile|winning hand with a pung (or kong) of north wind tiles, 白蛇[しろへび, はくじゃ]:albino Japanese rat snake, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 蛻[もぬけ]:shed skin of snake, insect, etc. (also place left behind), 蛻[ぬけがら]:cast-off skin (snake, insect, etc.)/husk/empty shell, 殻[から]:shell/husk/hull, 殻[がら]:chicken bones (e.g. for soup)|poor-quality coke (coal)|left-overs
この北白蛇神社は蛻(もぬけ)の殻だった
the Shrine of the Polar Snake was already empty like shed snake skin.
You should understand what I want you to do now.
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, こよみ:calendar/almanac, 頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
ここまで言えば
今度こそ私がこよみんに頼みたい仕事っていうのがなんだか わかったよね?
初代[しょだい]:first generation/founder, 捜索[そうさく]:search (esp. for someone or something missing)/manhunt|legally authorized search of a person, building, etc.
初代の彼の捜索だよ
Find him.
一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 目[め]:eye|eyesight|look||, 二人目[ふたりめ]:second person, 奴隷[どれい]:slave/servant|slavery, 同士[どうし, どし]:fellow/mutual/companion, 引く[ひく]:to pull|to draw (attention, etc.)|to draw back||, 合う[あう, おう]:to come together|to fit|to be profitable|
一人目と二人目で 奴隷同士
引かれ合うはずだから
You and he are slaves both;
you should be drawn to each other.
Shouldn't you have called upon Kagenui?
呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||, どちら:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives), 影[かげ]:shadow|reflection|ominous sign||
誰をおいても呼ぶべきは
どちらかと言えば影縫さんじゃなかったんですか?
斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 乃[の]:possessive particle, 木[き]:tree/shrub|wood, 木[もく]:Thursday|wood (first of the five elements), 主人[しゅじん]:head (of a household)|one's husband|(one's) employer|, 主人[あるじ]:head (of a household)/proprietor (of a store)|entertaining someone as one's guest, 不死身[ふじみ]:invulnerability/immortality/insensibility to pain, 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, 専門[せんもん]:speciality/specialty/subject of study, 暴力[ぼうりょく]:violence/mayhem, 陰陽[いんよう, おんみょう]:cosmic dual forces/yin and yang/sun and moon, etc., 師[し]:teacher|religious leader|specialist|
斧乃木ちゃんの主人の
不死身の怪異を専門とするあの暴力陰陽師
Ononoki's master, the violent hunter of immortal oddities.
制御[せいぎょ]:control/governing/checking
あいつは制御できない
I can't control her.
一生[いっしょう]:whole life/a lifetime|(the only, the greatest, etc.) of one's life, 髀肉[ひにく]:round meat/meat from a pig's thigh (from which ham is made), 嘆[たん]:sigh|grief/lamentation, 託つ[かこつ]:to complain about/to grumble/to make an excuse for, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
一生髀肉(ひにく)の嘆(たん)を託(かこ)っていてもらいたい
I want her to lament that she has no chance to display her power for her whole life.
What could possibly have provoked such a stance?
Lamenting
Thighs
Lamenting the absence of being able to do great deeds and
making a name for oneself. Exp.: Liu Bei's rule saw days of
peace, with no chances to ride into battle, and the thigh's of
warriors became fat.
Lamenting the absence of being able to do great deeds and
making a name for oneself. Exp.: Liu Bei's rule saw days of
peace, with no chances to ride into battle, and the thigh's of
warriors became fat.
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
この臥煙さんにそこまで言わせるって すごいな
I guess it'll be enough to have Ononoki on combat duty, then.
戦闘[せんとう]:battle/fight/combat, 要員[よういん]:essential member/necessary person/personnel, 斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 乃[の]:possessive particle, 木[き]:tree/shrub|wood, 木[もく]:Thursday|wood (first of the five elements), 十分[じっぷん, じゅっぷん]:10 minutes, 十分[じゅうぶん]:plenty|division into ten|perfectly
まあ でも 戦闘要員は
斧乃木ちゃんだけで十分なのか
No.
否[ひ]:no/the noes, 否[いいえ, いいや]:no|well|you're welcome
否
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 余接[よせつ]:cotangent, 経過[けいか]:passage/expiration/progress, 報告[ほうこく]:report/information, 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||, 時点[じてん]:point in time/occasion
昨日 その余接から経過報告を受けた時点で
After the report I received from her yesterday,
こよみ:calendar/almanac, 初代[しょだい]:first generation/founder, 接触[せっしょく]:touch/contact, 報告[ほうこく]:report/information, 時点[じてん]:point in time/occasion
つまり こよみんが初代の彼と
接触したという報告を聞いた時点で
after having reported that you made contact with him,
I called for backup.
一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 助っ人[すけっと]:helper/supporter/second, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
私はもう一人 助っ人を呼んでおいたよ
I have to go and meet them now.
そろそろ:slowly/quietly|soon, 迎える[むかえる]:to go out to meet|to receive|to accept (e.g. as a member of a group or family)||, いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good
そろそろ迎えに行かなきゃいけないのさ
助っ人[すけっと]:helper/supporter/second
で でも助っ人って
Backup?
斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 乃[の]:possessive particle, 木[き]:tree/shrub|wood, 木[もく]:Thursday|wood (first of the five elements), 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
斧乃木ちゃんだけじゃ駄目なんですか?
Is Ononoki really not enough?
Absolutely not.
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
駄目だ
決着をつける[けっちゃくをつける]:to settle (a dispute)
おねーさんは今日中に決着をつけるつもりだから
I want to finish this today.
意志[いし]:will/volition/intention, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, 意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information)
意志を持ち 意識を持ち
He has a will. He has his knowledge back.
最早[もはや]:already/now|no longer, エナジー:energy, ドレイン:drain, 恣意的[しいてき]:arbitrary, 使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful
最早エナジードレインを恣意的(しいてき)に使える彼は
He can use his energy drain at will.
The longer we wait, the stronger he'll become.
放置[ほうち]:leaving as is/leaving alone/leaving to chance, 強化[きょうか]:strengthening/intensifying/reinforcement
放置すればするほどに強化されていく
ゲーム:game
倍々々々々々ゲームだ
The stakes rise at every turn.
呑気[のんき, ノンキ]:carefree/optimistic/careless, 構える[かまえる]:to set up (a house, store, etc.)|to have at the ready (e.g. a gun)|to adopt a posture||, 完全[かんぜん]:perfection/completeness, 復活[ふっかつ]:revival (e.g. musical)/come-back|restoration, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
呑気に構えていると完全復活されてしまう
Unless we get going he will complete his revival.
負える[おえる]:to be able to bear|to be able to manage
そうなったら 手に負えない
Then it will be too late.
余弦[よげん]:cosine, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||, なくなる:to die, なくなる:to be lost (e.g. luggage)/to be missing|to be used up
そのときこそ 余弦を呼ぶしかなくなる
I'd have to call Yozuru.
Terrible
Monster
You make her sound like a weapon of mass destruction.
影[かげ]:shadow|reflection|ominous sign||, 非[ひ]:fault|going poorly|un-, 人道[じんどう, にんどう]:humanity|sidewalk|human realm, 兵器[へいき]:arms/weapons/ordnance, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
影縫さんを非人道兵器みたいに言ってるな
Terrible
Monster
喰う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
なんとしても 彼が人を喰う前に
殺してあげたい
I want to make sure that he's killed before he eats a human being.
出掛ける[でかける]:to go out (e.g. on an excursion or outing)/to leave|to be about to leave
ではおねーさんは出掛けてくるから
I'll take my leave.
Buy yourselves some breakfast if you're hungry, Koyomin.
お腹が空く[おなかがすく]:to become hungry/to get an empty stomach, 朝食[ちょうしょく, あさげ]:breakfast, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, なさる:to do, こよみ:calendar/almanac
お腹が空いたらこれで朝食でも
買ってきなさいな こよみん
どうするんだよ 忍
What should we do, Shinobu?
どうもこうもあるまい
Nothing.
イレギュラー:irregular, 先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), 専門家[せんもんか]:specialist/expert/professional, プラン:plan, 通り[とおり]:avenue|coming and going|flow (of water, air, etc.)||, 通り[どおり]:in accordance with|roughly|Street
イレギュラーはあったにせよ
ここから先はあの専門家のプラン通りに行くじゃろう
It didn't go according to plan for her,
but I expect it now will.
今晩[こんばん]:tonight/this evening, 始末[しまつ]:management|course of events|end result (usu. bad)|
そやつはどうあれ 今晩中に始末される
Whatever he is, he'll be dealt with before the day is over.
それだけじゃよ
That is all.
儂[わし]:I/me (used by elderly males)
儂らがもう 何をするまでもあるまい
There's nothing for us to do here.
儂[わし]:I/me (used by elderly males), 近付く[ちかづく, ちかずく]:to approach/to draw near|to get acquainted with, パワーアップ:making more powerful, 可能性[かのうせい]:potentiality/likelihood/possibility
儂が近付くことでパワーアップする
可能性があるということじゃから
It's possible that he'll become stronger in my vicinity,
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, ともかく:anyhow/anyway/somehow or other, 儂[わし]:I/me (used by elderly males), 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face, 合わす[あわす]:to match (rhythm, speed, etc.)|to join together|to face||
お前様はともかく
儂は顔を合わすこともないじゃろう
so, perhaps unlike you, I will never see him.
儂[わし]:I/me (used by elderly males), 始末[しまつ]:management|course of events|end result (usu. bad)|
儂の知らんところで 始末はつくよ
This will be handled without me.
Also, my master... Don't overthink this.
余計[よけい]:too many|unnecessary|abundantly, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, 我が[わが]:my/our/one's own, あるじ:head (of a household)/proprietor (of a store)|entertaining someone as one's guest, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
言っておくが 余計なことを考えるなよ
我があるじ様
She stoked your jealousy because she found it amusing,
面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant, 半分[はんぶん]:half, 半分[はんぷん]:half minute, 煽る[あおる]:to fan (oneself, flames, etc.)|to flap|to instigate||
あの女が面白半分に煽るようなことを言っておったが
儂[わし]:I/me (used by elderly males), 眷属[けんぞく]:(one's) family/dependents|follower, 一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 目[め]:eye|eyesight|look||, 二人目[ふたりめ]:second person
儂にとっては 眷属に一人目も二人目もない
but, to me, nobody is first or second.
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 儂[わし]:I/me (used by elderly males), 順番[じゅんばん]:turn (in line)/order of things/sequential order, なんぞ:et cetera/etc./and the like, なんぞ:something|what, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
五百年から生きとる儂に 順番なんぞ関係あるか
Do you think sequences matter to me
after having lived for five hundred years?
先日[せんじつ]:the other day/a few days ago, 昔話[むかしばなし]:old tale/folk tale|reminiscence, ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 前置き[まえおき]:preface/introduction/preamble
先日 昔話をしたときに
ちゃんと前置きしてやったはずじゃよな?
Didn't I preface my story with this the other day?
前置き[まえおき]:preface/introduction/preamble
ま 前置きって
Preface?
くだる:to descend/to go down|to be handed down (of an order, judgment, etc.), 嫉妬[しっと]:jealousy/envy
くだらん嫉妬をするな
Envy is unbecoming.
可愛い[かわいい, かわゆい]:cute|dear|cute little, 焼きもち[やきもち]:jealousy|roasted rice cake, 程度[ていど]:degree/amount/grade
可愛い焼きもち程度にしておけ
A little jealousy is cute and fine by me.
悩む[なやむ]:to be worried/to be troubled
悩むな
Don't grieve.
儂[わし]:I/me (used by elderly males), 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
今の儂にはお前様しかおらぬ
You're the only one I have right now.
家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, 夜[よる, よ]:evening/night, 夜[や]:counter for nights, 絶食[ぜっしょく]:fasting
家にはまだ帰れないにしても
このまま夜まで絶食というわけにはいくまい
Even though I can't go home, there's no way I'd survive until tonight without eating.
ペアリング:pairing, 切れる[きれる]:to break|to be injured|to wear out||, 現在[げんざい]:now/current/present, 空腹[くうふく]:hunger, とは言え[とはいえ]:though/although/be that as it may
忍とのペアリングが切れている現在
僕も空腹に強いとは言えないし
I'm not a very big eater right now
since my link to Shinobu is broken,
後輩[こうはい]:junior (at work, school, etc.)/younger people/younger student, 飢える[うえる, かつえる]:to starve/to thirst/to be hungry, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration
後輩を飢えさせておくわけにもいかない
but I can't let Kanbaru starve either.
I request donuts.
ドーナツ:doughnut/donut, 所望[しょもう]:desire/request/wish
ドーナツを所望する
走る[はしる]:to run|to travel (movement of vehicles)|to hurry to||
私がひとっ走り行ってこようか?
Want me to grab them?
ほとんど:mostly/nearly/practically, 働く[はたらく]:to work|to function|to commit (e.g. a crime)|
いや ここまでほとんど働いていないから
No. I haven't done much so far.
買い出し[かいだし]:going out to shop/going shopping|buying in quantity, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
買い出しくらいはさせて欲しい
Let me at least get you all food.
わかった
All right.
じゃあ私は忍ちゃんを見ておく
I'll look at Shinobu.
I'll look after Shinobu.
面倒を見る[めんどうをみる]:to care for someone/to look after someone
私は忍ちゃんの面倒を見ておく
大丈夫かな...
Should I leave them alone?
初対面[しょたいめん]:first meeting/first interview with, 近い[ちかい]:near|close (in time)|close (relationship)||, 二人[ふたり, ににん]:two persons/two people/pair, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
ほぼ初対面に近い忍と神原を二人きりにしてしまって
This is practically their first time together.
I can't really take Shinobu with me into town.
状況[じょうきょう]:state of affairs (around you)/situation/circumstances, 連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person), 買物[かいもの]:shopping/purchased goods
しかし今の状況で
忍を連れて買物に行くわけにもいくまい
The sun gives us some protection,
but I should still have her remain here.
昼間[ひるま, ちゅうかん]:daytime/during the day/time from sunrise until sunset, 安全[あんぜん]:safety|security, 大人しい[おとなしい]:obedient/docile/quiet, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
昼間だから安全とは言っても
忍には大人しくしておいてもらうべきだろう
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 買い出し[かいだし]:going out to shop/going shopping|buying in quantity, ついで:next/secondly/subsequently, ついで:opportunity/occasion, 図々しい[ずうずうしい]:impudent/shameless, 恐縮[きょうしゅく]:feeling obliged/being grateful|shrinking back in fear, 使い[つかい]:errand|messenger|familiar spirit|, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
じゃあ阿良々木先輩 買い出しのついでに 図々しくて恐縮だが
ひとつお使いをお願いしてしまってもよいだろうか
I'm extremely sorry to impose on you,
but could you do something for me when you buy food?
言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say
なんだよ なんでも言えよ
Sure. Spit it out.
Buy me a book.
本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
本を買ってきて欲しいのだ
発売[はつばい]:sale/offering for sale/release (for sale), 新刊[しんかん]:new book/new publication
今日発売の新刊なのだが
It went on sale today.
発売[はつばい]:sale/offering for sale/release (for sale)
今日発売?
Today?
ふうん:misfortune/bad luck/ill luck, ふうん:hmm/well ...|roughly
ふうん いいよ
Sure.
買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
じゃあ買ってきてやるよ
I'll buy it for you.
ライト:light, ノベル:novel
ライトノベルなのだが いいだろうか?
It's a light novel. Still fine?
おいおい:Hey!/Wait a minute!|boohoo, おいおい:gradually/by degrees/little by little, 困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered
おいおい 困るねえ神原くん
Come now, Kanbaru.
ライト:light, ノベル:novel, 退廃[たいはい]:degeneration/decadence/deterioration, 芸術[げいじゅつ]:(fine) art/the arts, 扱い[あつかい]:treatment/service, 連中[れんちゅう, れんじゅう]:company/lot|troupe, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
僕がライトノベルを退廃芸術扱いする
連中の仲間に見えるのかい?
Do I look like the kind of guy who treats light novels as degenerate art?
ばりばり:tearing/ripping|crunching, 少女[しょうじょ, おとめ]:little girl/maiden|female between 17 and 20 years old (ritsuryo period), 漫画[まんが, マンガ]:cartoon/comic/comic strip, 表紙[ひょうし]:front cover/binding|appearing on the cover of a magazine, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, 男子[だんし]:youth/young man, 高校生[こうこうせい]:senior high school student
ばりばりの少女漫画だって
表紙を上にして買う男子高校生だぜ
I'm a boy in high school buying teary
shoujo manga with the cover facing up.
書物[しょもつ]:books, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, 恥ずかしい[はずかしい]:shy/ashamed|disgraceful
書物を買うのを恥ずかしいとか
思ったりしないって
Nothing I buy could embarrass me.
安心[あんしん]:relief/peace of mind, 安心[あんじん]:obtaining peace of mind through faith or ascetic practice
それを聞いて安心した
That's great to hear.
タイトル:title
で タイトルは?
So what's the title?
鬼畜[きちく]:brute/savage/fiend, ギャルソン:(male) waiter, ハーフ:half, ボーイ:boy
"鬼畜ギャルソン・ハーフボーイをハフハフ!"
"The Brutal Garçon Devours The Half-Boy."
The Brutal Garçon Devours The Half-Boy
There's nothing light in that light novel!
ライト:light, ノベル:novel
それライトノベルのライトじゃない奴だろ!
What kind of book do you want me to buy?!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
お前 先輩にどんな本を買わせるつもりなんだよ!
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess
結局ＢＬ読んでんじゃねーか...
It's just gay softcore porn, right?
しかも:moreover/furthermore|nevertheless, タイトル:title
しかもなんだそのタイトル
And what's with that title?
A book is more than its title.
The Brutal Garçon Devours The Half-Boy!
小説[しょうせつ]:novel/(short) story, タイトル:title
小説はタイトルがすべてじゃないだろう
昨今[さっこん, さくこん]:nowadays/recently, 文芸[ぶんげい]:literature/art and literature/belles-lettres, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, タイトル:title, 重視[じゅうし]:importance/stress|to take something seriously
昨今は文芸の世界もタイトルが
重視されるようになってきたけれど
The art world has been stressing
the importance of a good title lately,
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, 名作[めいさく]:masterpiece, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 適当[てきとう]:suitable/proper|noncommittal, タイトル:title
昔の名作なんて
本当に適当につけられたと思しきタイトルも多いぞ
but history is full of great classics with whimsical names.
The Brutal Garçon Devours The Half-Boy!
No Title
Young
Murderous Attendant
Ah, Fall
Abababa
Who
Yellow Face
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 小説[しょうせつ]:novel/(short) story, 内容[ないよう]:subject/contents/matter
まあ 確かに小説は内容だからな
I guess a book really is more than its cover.
The Brutal Garçon Devours The Half-Boy!
Volume 21
本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||, 内容[ないよう]:subject/contents/matter, 期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope
しかし その本の内容は
期待していいのか?
What can readers expect of that book?
Much indeed!
特に[とくに]:particularly/especially, 今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, 発売[はつばい]:sale/offering for sale/release (for sale), シリーズ:series, 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 弾[たま]:ball|bead (of sweat, dew, etc.)|ball (in sports)||, 弾[だん]:counter for parts (of a story, etc.), 有識者[ゆうしきしゃ]:expert/knowledgeable person, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope, 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive
特に今回発売されるシリーズ第二十一弾は
有識者の間でも期待が高い
This is the twenty-first book in the series,
and it was warmly anticipated by experts.
The new volume is coming——
Brutal assault is my favorite!
So looking forward to the release date.
The new volume is coming——
Brutal assault is my favorite!
So looking forward to the release date.
Anonymous Expert
That's way too many books in a series!
シリーズ:series, 続く[つづく]:to continue|to continue (without a break)|to occur again and again||, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by, 有識者[ゆうしきしゃ]:expert/knowledgeable person
シリーズ続き過ぎだろ!
誰だよ有識者って!
And who are those experts, exactly?!
It's expected the author will finally lift the great mystery that has driven the novels since the first volume.
最新[さいしん]:latest/newest/late-breaking (news), 刊[かん]:publication/edition (e.g. morning, evening, special)/published in (year), いよいよ:more and more/all the more|at last, 一巻[いっかん, ひとまき]:one roll|one book|first volume|, 一巻[いちまき]:one entire scroll, 提示[ていじ]:presentation/exhibit/suggest, シリーズ:series, 最大[さいだい]:biggest/greatest/largest, 謎[なぞ]:riddle/puzzle|enigmatic
最新刊ではいよいよ
一巻から提示されていたシリーズ最大の謎
Great Mystery
"Grandson of gal?"
That being, "Is the Brutal Garçon a gal's grandson?"
Great Mystery
"Grandson of gal?"
鬼畜[きちく]:brute/savage/fiend, ギャルソン:(male) waiter, ギャル:gyaru/(young) woman adhering to a fashion trend usually marked by brown or blond-dyed hair, gaudy clothes and accessories, 孫[まご]:grandchild, 明かす[あかす]:to pass (e.g. the night)/to spend|to reveal
鬼畜ギャルソンがギャルの孫なのかどうかが
明かされるのだ
He probably is!
Heaven Girl
Great Mystery
"Grandson of gal?"
Bloodstained Serveuse
Hell Boy
Brutal Garçon
多分[たぶん]:perhaps/probably|generous, ギャル:gyaru/(young) woman adhering to a fashion trend usually marked by brown or blond-dyed hair, gaudy clothes and accessories, 孫[まご]:grandchild
それは多分ギャルの孫だよ!
Did the author really drag that out to twenty-one volumes?
作者[さくしゃ]:author/authoress/writer, 謎[なぞ]:riddle/puzzle|enigmatic, 巻[まき]:roll (e.g. of cloth)|winding|volume (of book), 巻[かん]:volume (of book)/reel (of film), 引っ張る[ひっぱる]:to pull|to string (lines)|to pull towards oneself (e.g. someone's sleeve)||
作者の人 そんな謎を
二十巻も引っ張っちゃったのか!?
Heaven Girl
Great Mystery
"Grandson of gal?"
In fact, when I told you "Dig in!" yesterday,
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, 昨夜[ゆうべ, ゆう]:evening|last night, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 召し上がる[めしあがる]:to eat/to drink, 台詞[せりふ, かはく]:speech/words/one's lines
実は昨夜 私が阿良々木先輩に言った
"召し上がれ♪"という台詞は
Great Mystery
"Grandson of gal?"
Keyword
"Dig In"
that was lifted from the main character of the novel.
シリーズ:series, メイン:main/principal part, キャラ:(fictional) character, 借りる[かりる]:to borrow/to have a loan|to rent
そのシリーズのメインキャラから
お借りしたものだ
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, ボーイズラブ:comics or novels about male homosexuality, targetted at young women, 台詞[せりふ, かはく]:speech/words/one's lines
まさかボーイズラブの台詞だったとは!
A gay character said that?!
I thought it was cute!
買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
えー 買ってきてくれないのかー?
You're not going to buy it for me?
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
じゃあもう 帰ろっかなー
I'm gonna go home, then.
買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
買って来るよ買って来ればいいんだろ!
I will! Are you happy now?!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
ああそうだ 阿良々木先輩
Oh, right, Araragi.
ブラジャー:bra/brassiere, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
できたらでいいから
ブラジャーを買ってきてくれないかな
Could you also buy a bra for me?
No, I really can't.
買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
それはできないから買ってきてくれないよ
No. You can!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
大丈夫 阿良々木先輩ならできる
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 期待をかける[きたいをかける]:to hang one's hopes on/to expect from, 過ぎ[すぎ]:past/after|too (much)
神原くんは何かにつけ
阿良々木先輩に期待をかけ過ぎなんだよ
You have excessive expectations of me in a lot of ways.
デザイン:design, 問う[とう]:to ask|to charge (e.g. with a crime)|without regard to|
デザインは問わない
The design doesn't matter.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, センス:taste (in fashion, music, etc.)/sense (e.g. of humour)/flair, 選ぶ[えらぶ]:to choose/to select
阿良々木先輩のセンスで選んでくれ
Just pick what you like.
Don't ask me about what I'd pick, please.
センス:taste (in fashion, music, etc.)/sense (e.g. of humour)/flair, 問う[とう]:to ask|to charge (e.g. with a crime)|without regard to|, ブラジャー:bra/brassiere, 選び[えらび]:choosing/selecting/deciding (on)
センスを問わないで ブラジャー選びの
There's an enormous variety of designs,
but what matters most is contained within.
なあに:what|what?, ブラジャー:bra/brassiere, 柄[え]:handle/grip|stalk (of a mushroom, leaf, etc.), 柄[がら]:pattern|body build|essential qualities|, 千差万別[せんさばんべつ, せんさまんべつ]:an infinite variety of/multifarious/being extremely varied and wide-ranging, 結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 大切[たいせつ, たいせち]:important|beloved|careful, 大切[おおぎり]:large cut (e.g. of meat)|last piece of the day's programme/last act of a play, 中身[なかみ]:contents/interior/substance
なあに ブラジャーの柄も千差万別だが
結局 大切なのは中身だ
Don't make it sound deep.
台詞[せりふ, かはく]:speech/words/one's lines, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
いい台詞みたいに言うな
I'm at the limit for going without one.
ノーブラ:not wearing a bra/being bra-less, 限界[げんかい]:limit/bound, 迎える[むかえる]:to go out to meet|to receive|to accept (e.g. as a member of a group or family)||
ノーブラの限界を迎えた
中身[なかみ]:contents/interior/substance, 大切[たいせつ, たいせち]:important|beloved|careful, 大切[おおぎり]:large cut (e.g. of meat)|last piece of the day's programme/last act of a play
本当に中身を大切にしたい
I have the need to feel contained.
ブラジャー:bra/brassiere
何かにつけというか
今はブラジャーをつけたい
Only a bra can hold me in, now.
けじめをつける:to draw the line (between two situations)/to make a clear distinction|to take clear responsibility for (mistakes, etc.)
けじめをつけようよ
I've had enough.
あった
Here they are.
鬼畜[きちく]:brute/savage/fiend, ギャルソン:(male) waiter, ハーフ:half, ボーイ:boy
鬼畜ギャルソン・ハーフボーイをハフハフ!
"The Brutal Garçon Devours The Half-Boy."
タイトル:title, 負け[まけ]:defeat/loss/losing (a game), すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength), 表紙[ひょうし]:front cover/binding|appearing on the cover of a magazine
タイトル負けしないすげえ表紙だ
The cover is valiantly competing with the title!
The Brutal Garçon Devours The Half-Boy Part One
Buying just these two books is kind of embarrassing.
本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||, 二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 冊[さつ]:counter for books|volume, 冊[さく]:imperial edict to confer nobility titles (in ancient China), 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, やっぱり:too/also|still, 照れる[てれる]:to be shy/to be bashful/to feel awkward, ものがある:sentence-ending expression of strong judgement
この本二冊だけを買うというのは
やっぱりちょっと 照れるものがあるな
21st Book Published!
The mystery: Is the garçon the grandson of a gal?
"Dig In"
Brutal Garçon series 1-20 on sale!!
I think it's not very manly to buy other books to disguise something you bought,
本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, 際[きわ, ぎわ]:edge/brink|time, 際[さい]:on the occasion of/circumstances/juncture, カムフラージュ:camouflage, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish, ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
本を買う際にカムフラージュの本を買うなんて
男らしくないと思う僕ではあるけれど
The Brutal Garçon Devours The Half-Boy Part Two
逆[ぎゃく]:reverse|converse (of a hypothesis, etc.)|inverse (function), 逆[さか]:inverse/reverse, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish, 発揮[はっき]:exhibition/demonstration/show, 思える[おもえる]:to seem/to appear likely
しかしここでは逆に男らしさを
発揮しないほうがいいようにも思える
but it's probably still better than not concealing the unmanliness of these books.
ペアリング:pairing, 組む[くむ]:to cross (legs or arms)|to put together|to braid||, 今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, くらやみ:darkness/the dark, 切る[きる]:to cut|to sever (connections, ties)|to turn off (e.g. the light)||, ことによる:depending on the circumstances|due to (with modifying verb)
そう言えば 忍とのペアリングも 思えば組まれてから長いけれども
今回 あの"くらやみ"によってそれが切られたことによって
That reminds me that, since my link to Shinobu was severed by the darkness,
Historical Novels
Japanese Literature
久方ぶり[ひさかたぶり]:long time (since the last time)/many days, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance, 一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 行動[こうどう]:action/conduct/behaviour
久方ぶりに僕は 本当の意味で
一人で行動しているのだった
I'm truly alone for the first time in a while.
I'm my own master!
自由[じゆう]:freedom/liberty/as it pleases you, 行動[こうどう]:action/conduct/behaviour
自由行動
Freedom!
フリーダム:free
フリーダム
束の間[つかのま]:moment/brief time/brief, 自由[じゆう]:freedom/liberty/as it pleases you, 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost, 気にする[きにする]:to mind (negative nuance)/to care about/to worry, 間隙[かんげき]:gap, ロスタイム:loss of time/lost time, せめて:at least/at most, せめて:offense/offence/method of attack, 満喫[まんきつ]:having enough of (food, drink, etc.)/having one's fill|fully enjoying
ならばこの束の間の自由を 人の目も怪異の目も気にしなくていい
間隙(かんげき)のロスタイムを せめて満喫するべきではないのか
Then let us enjoy this ephemeral freedom, this little pocket of lost time.
Idol - Actress
Photo collection corner
Mature Woman
Photo Collection
Gravure Idol!
Slightly Perverted Older Sister
Super-Hot Photo Collection
Gravure
It seems that having fun with Shinobu, Ononoki, and Hachikuji lately
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 斧[おの]:axe/hatchet, 乃[の]:possessive particle, 木[き]:tree/shrub|wood, 木[もく]:Thursday|wood (first of the five elements), 寺[てら]:temple (Buddhist), 寺[じ]:counter for temples, 楽しい[たのしい]:enjoyable/fun, 遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys
どうも最近 忍や斧乃木ちゃん
八九寺と楽しく遊んでいることが多かったせいで
ロリコン:Lolita complex (sexual attraction to children, esp. young girls), 疑惑[ぎわく]:doubt/misgivings/distrust, 増す[ます]:to increase/to grow
僕へのロリコン疑惑は 日に日に増している
has led to me being increasingly suspected of being a lolicon.
In keeping with the zeitgeist and in view of our age,
時勢[じせい]:spirit of the age/trends/conditions, 時節柄[じせつがら]:in these times/in times like these/the season being what it is, 疑惑[ぎわく]:doubt/misgivings/distrust, 晴らす[はらす]:to dispel|to accomplish a goal|to make it sunny
時勢も時勢 時節柄も時節柄
疑惑を晴らすためにも
I ought to dispel these suspicions by opting for the opposite.
逆[ぎゃく]:reverse|converse (of a hypothesis, etc.)|inverse (function), 逆[さか]:inverse/reverse, 打つ[うつ]:to hit|to strike (noon, etc.)|to beat (rhythmically, e.g. pulse, waves, etc.)||, 打つ[ぶつ]:to hit (a person)/to strike/to beat
ここは逆を打っておくべきだろう
Housewife Photo Studio
Mature Lady Cosplayer
Thirty Sweet Temptations
Mature Body
Athletic and Mature Collection
MILFs.
熟女[じゅくじょ]:attractive mature lady
つまり熟女だ
Employees Laughing
二人目[ふたりめ]:second person
やあ 二人目
Hey, number two.
伝言[でんごん]:verbal message/word, 伝言[つてこと]:verbal message/word|rumour, 伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
キスショットに伝言は伝えてくれたかのう?
Did you give my message to Kiss-Shot?
I hear your laughter beyond the door
You were supposed to be with me forever
I breathed onto the classroom window and wrote your name
only to panic and wipe it with my sleeve
I heard your voice from the hallway
and went home in hurry to hide my feelings
At some point I became unable
to talk to you normally
I can hear your laughter beyond the door
You were supposed to be next to me forever
You knew how I felt
even when I said nothing
Now I know how important you were to me,
but we will never see each other again